PROFESSOR: Let's do an interlude, which
is going to help us see how
MDPs, which we've just studied for a
unit here and reinforcement learning,
which we're about to do--
how they connect.
So let's imagine the agent, which is
basically us, for this interlude,
walks into a game where there are two
slot machines that it can play.
There's a blue slot machine
and a red slot machine.
And they behave a little
bit differently.
When you pull the handle on the blue
slot machine, you receive $1.
So this is basically a
good slot machine.
Real slot machines aren't
quite so nice.
You pull the handle, you get $1.
What about the red slot machine?
You pull the handle, and you're
either going to get $2 or $0.
It's a little more exciting, right?
How should the agent act?
Well, let me tell you the MDP then
we'll figure out how the
agent should act.
You can think of this as a
Markov decision process.
It's actually a super boring one.
The state structure isn't
very interesting.
The interesting thing is the actions.
You've got the blue action, where you
play the blue bandit, and you've got
the red action, where you
play the red bandit.
There are two states in this.
But they're really shouldn't be.
In essence, you're always in the same
state, which is, what should I do?
The reason why we have two states in
this formalization is because, in
order to actually make this idea work
out, that you might get $0 or you
might get $2, it's a little tricky
because the rewards so far haven't
been non-deterministic.
They're deterministic, it's a result
state that is not deterministic.
So in order to have different rewards
for winning and losing, I need
different states for winning
and missing.
So here's one way to
formalize this MDP.
The actions are blue and red.
And the states are, I just won
or I just lost the last pool.
So if you look at this, let's first
look at the blue action.
Remember the blue bandit, the blue
slot machine, always wins.
So with probability 1, you get $1 and
transition to the I just won state.
The red bandit wins 75% of the time and
gives you $2 and loses 25% of the
time and gives you zero dollars.
And so transition structure
reflects that.
It's a little redundant because the red
action does the same thing whether
you just won or just lost.
That's the kind of independence that you
can't see from the diagram here.
Let's say there's no discount
because then things are just
going to get messy.
Let's say there's 100 times step, so
that the answer isn't that everything
has infinite value.
No discount, 100 time steps.
And if we look at this, we can
see that win and loss, really
there's only one value.
It doesn't matter which state you're
at because the actions do the same
thing from the states.
So let's think about this MDP.
We are going to do offline planning.
So we're going to solve this MDP.
And we're going to solve
it in our heads.
So let's think, you know the MDP.
We can determine things
through computation.
What the value for playing blue?
You always get $1.
And if you only play blue, that's a
policy, if you only play blue, you're
going to play it 100
times and get $100.
So assuming dollars here are the
utilities for this agent, the value of
the play blue policy is 100.
The value of the play
red policy is 150.
Why?
Because we're going to play 100 times,
and on average, I mean, who knows what
will actually happen.
But on average, 3/4 of those
are going to be $2.
And when we multiply all that
together, we get 150.
So here's two policies
and their values.
How do I figure out those values?
I did the math, right?
I thought about the MDP.
I did some computation.
In principle, I ran value iteration, but
this is so simple an MDP I didn't
even have to do that.
OK, so I used math and my knowledge of
the MDP to figure out the values.
Did we actually play this game yet?
No, we have not played this game.
We have just thought deep and
profound thoughts about it.
I know the optimal policy.
What's the optimal policy?
It's always play red.
OK, that was offline planning.
We did not play the game.
We used our knowledge of the MDP to
figure out various things, such as
values of policies, optimal
actions, and so on.
Now let's actually play.
And remember that 150,000?
That was an average, right?
Let's see what actually happens.
So we're going to play.
And we decided that the awesome
policy is to play red.
So we're not even going to look
at the blue slot machine here.
So let's play.
We pull the lever.
We get $2, great.
What happens next?
We play red again, $2.
And again, $0, $2, $2,
$2, $2, $0, $0, $0.
OK, well we just played 10 times.
We could imagine that that was
100, but we played 10 times.
So we just played our policy.
How did we do?
Looks like we got $12.
What did the values suggest
we would get?
Well, on average, we should
have gotten 15.
So we were a little bit unlucky,
but not ridiculously unlucky.
Here, it's very important.
We solved it offline, in our heads.
We actually played in the real world,
using the policy that we determined to
be optimal in our heads.
This playing, where we got the two and
the zero, and we were slightly
unlucky, that actually happened.
We actually won real fake money, OK?
Let's change the rules.
You still have these
two slot machines.
Blue always pays out $1.
Red always pays out $0 or $2.
But we don't know the probabilities.
All right, whats the optimal policy?
What should I do?
You 're like, I don't know, right?
We don't know the MDP.
And if you don't know the MDP,
you can't figure out the
values in your head.
And you can't figure out whether playing
red or playing blue is the
better policy.
You can could only use those offline
planning methods when
you know the MDP.
And you don't.
OK, so what do we do?
Do we give up and go home?
Or do we play some slots?
Let's play.
All right, what would you like to do.
What should you do?
Everyone wants to play red.
Are you sure that is
the optimal policy?
I mean, who knows, right?
So what we're going to play red.
Why?
Why are we doing this?
Because red might be good.
And we're not going to
know until we try.
So we play red.
$0.
Player red again, $0.
Red, $0.
Now what you want to do?
Who wants red?
$2.
$0.
Blue?
All right.
Blue gets you $1.
[LAUGHTER]
What's next?
Blue, ok it got you $1.
What's next Red, we got $2.
Red, we got $0.
$0, $0, are you ever going
to give up on red?
OK, maybe you will eventually give up.
Smart move.
OK, so this is a different setting.
This is a setting where
there is an MDP.
Red has a payoff.
And you know that it has a payoff.
But you don't know what it is.
So in essence, there's an MDP, but
you don't know its parameters.
How are you going to figure
out what to do?
Well, it's no longer the case that you
can close your eyes, and meditate, and
figure out what's optimal
for that MDP.
What you have to do is, you have to do
a kind of optimal amount of discovery
mixed in with trying not
to lose all your money.
What just happened here when
we played that game?
What happened was not planning.
It was learning.
So this is the first time in this course
where we see not just this idea
of planning on the basis of something
that you know, but learning from
experiences that you have, specifically,
you just did
reinforcement learning.
You took actions and received
rewards, and thereby
learned how to act optimally.
There was an MDP, but you couldn't solve
it with pure computation because
you didn't know all of its parameters.
You needed to actually act and pull
the lever to figure it out.
Because of that, you just saw all
of the important ideas in
reinforcement learning.
So let me go through some of them now.
We'll see all of these again.
One of this idea of exploration.
And that is, you have to try unknown
actions to gather information.
Another idea is exploitation.
And exploitation says, eventually,
you have to use what you know.
You can't just keep pulling the red
lever forever out of curiosity of just
exactly how bad it is.
At some point, you have to do things
that you know are successful.
And balancing exploration and
exploitation is a big problem in
reinforcement learning.
There's an idea of regret.
And that is, even though that you all
did the right thing, you played red
for a while until it was obvious that it
was not very good, even though you
acted optimally, in the sense that
given what you knew, that was the
right thing to do, you still incurred
what's called regret, which is you
didn't do as well as if you would
actually known the MDP and used the
optimal policy with respect
to the actual in MDP.
And of course, there's always going to
be regret against perfect knowledge
because you need to make some
mistakes in order to figure
out how to be optimal.
You observed sampling.
Because there's chance involved, you
have to try things many times before
you actually know how they're
going to shake out.
And you still never really know.
You also saw it was more difficult.
This is the simplest MDP you
could possibly imagine.
And it was instantly obvious when I
showed you the numbers that you should
always play red in the original case.
All I have to do is take that payoff
probability away, and suddenly we have
a hard problem of how long to play
red, and when to give up,
or if to give up.
So these problems become much more
difficult, even the MDP is simple,
your lack of knowledge then triggers a
much more difficult reasoning problem
about how you should act.